# Yen-Hsun Lin, PhD | Curriculum Vitæ

Institute of Physics - Academia Sinica, Taiwan

☑ yenhsun@phys.ncku.edu.tw

yenhsunlin

(+886) 912 907 618

Hsinchu, Taiwan

### **SUMMARY**

I am an astroparticle phenomenologist specializing in multimessenger astronomy and dark matter detection. My research focuses on topics such as supernova neutrino-boosted dark matter and the effects of self-interacting dark matter on compact stars, the Sun, and Earth. I work with members of DUNE/COHERENT to reduce systematic uncertainties in DUNE-like detectors. I was also in the JUNO collaboration, with the role of estimating its sensitivity to Solar captured dark matter. With a background in astroparticle physics and extensive research experience, I have developed a deep understanding of dark matter studies and their applications.

# RESEARCH TOPIC

Astroparticle physics, dark matter physics in compact stars and supernovæ, nuclear astrophysics, scientific computations (parallel and GPU computing), Bayesian inference and Monte Carlo simulations

# **EDUCATION**

National Chiao Tung University

PhD of the Institute of Physics Aug. 2011 - Jul. 2016

Advisor: Prof. Lin, Guey-Lin

**Thesis:** *Indirect detection of dark matter through neutrinos* 

National Chiao Tung University Hsinchu, Taiwan

MS of the Institute of Physics (Direct to PhD program)

Aug. 2010 - Jul. 2011

Advisor: Prof. Lin, Guey-Lin

National Chiao Tung University Hsinchu, Taiwan

BS of the Department of Electrophysics Aug. 2006 - Jul. 2010

WORKING EXPERIENCE

Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica Taipei, Taiwan

Postdoctoral Scholar Aug. 2023 - present

Host: Dr. Wu, Meng-Ru

School of Physics, Melbourne University

Melbourne, Australia

Visiting Scholar Oct. 2023 - Nov. 2023

**Host:** Prof. Bell, Nicole

Physics Division, National Center for Theoretical Sciences

Taipei, Taiwan

Postdoctoral Scholar Dec. 2021 - Jul. 2023

Independent position with travel funding

#### Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica

Distinguished Postdoctoral Scholar

Independent position with grant

Host: Dr. Wu, Meng-Ru

#### Department of Physics, National Cheng Kung University

Postdoctoral Scholar

Host: Prof. Chen, Chuan-Hung

#### Taipei, Taiwan

Aug. 2019 - Dec. 2021

Tainan, Taiwan

Oct. 2017 - Jul. 2019

# Honors and Awards

#### **NCTS Postdoc Paper Award**

O Awarded by the Physics Division, National Center for Theoretical Sciences

# Best Research Paper Award for Junior Research Investigator

O Awarded by the Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica

# Selected Participant of the 13<sup>th</sup> HOPE Meeting with Nobel Laureates

Representative of Taiwan

#### **Distinguished Postdoctoral Scholar**

Independent position with grant, selected by the Academia Sinica

#### Annual Best PhD Thesis in Physical Science

Best PhD Thesis of the year, awarded by the Taiwan Physical Society

### Selected Honorary Member of the Phi Tau Phi Scholastic Society

Issued to the student graduated with top score

Taiwan, 2019

Taiwan, 2024

*Taiwan, 2024* 

Japan, 2022

# Taiwan, 2017

#### Taiwan, 2016

# **INVITED TALKS AT CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS**

# The 3<sup>rd</sup> International Joint Workshop on the Standard Model and Beyond and the 11<sup>th</sup> KIAS Workshop on Particle Physics and Cosmology

 $\circ$  **Title:** Detection of SN $\nu$  BDM in current and future large underground detectors

O Host: Korea Institute for Advanced Study (KIAS)

#### Interplay of Nuclear, Neutrino and BSM Physics at Low-Energies

Seattle, 2023

Jeju, 2023

- O Title: Searching for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos
- **Host:** Institute for Nuclear Theory (INT 23–85w)

#### Supernova Early Warning System (SNEWS) Online Seminar

US, 2023

- O Title: Searching for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos
- Host: SNEWS Institutions (invited by Alec Habig)

#### Theory Meeting Experiment: Particle Physics and Cosmology

Quy Nhơn, 2023

- O Title: Light DM constraints from neutron stars and supernova neutrinos
- O Host: International Centre for Interdisciplinary Science and Education (19<sup>th</sup> Recontres du Vietnam)

#### **NCTS Annual Theory Meeting**

*Taipei*, 2022

- O Title: Light DM constraints from neutron stars and supernova neutrinos
- Host: National Center for Theoretical Sciences

#### Dark Matter in Compact Objects, Stars, and in Low Energy Experiments

Seattle, 2022

- O Title: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos
- O Host: Institute for Nuclear Theory (INT 22–2b)

#### Particle Physics Phenomenology Workshop (PPP 14)

*Taipei*, 2022

- O Title: Searching the afterglow from supernova neutrino boosted dark matter
- Host: National Center for Theoretical Sciences

#### Sydney Consortium for Particle Physics and Cosmology Seminar

Sydney, 2021

- O Title: Searching light to heavy dark matter by supernova neutrinos and neutron star temperature
- O Host: University of New South Wales Sydney and University of Sydney (Sydney-CPPC)

#### Mini-workshop on Novel Experimental and Astrophysical Probes for Dark Matter

Taipei, 2021

- O Title: Exploring dark matter with compact stars
- O Host: Academia Sinica

#### **NCTS Annual Theory Meeting**

Taipei, 2019

- O Title: Probing the isospin violation of self-interacting dark matter through old neutron stars
- Host: National Tsing Hua University

# Particle Physics Phenomenology Workshop (PPP 13)

Taipei, 2019

- O Title: Probing self-interacting dark matter through neutron stars
- O Host: National Taiwan Normal University

#### **COLLABORATION MEMBERSHIP**

#### With Members of DUNE/COHERENT Collaborations

US, 2020-present

- Collaborating with Dr. Gianluca Petrillo and Dr. Yun-Tse Tsai from SLAC
- $\circ$  Study the impact on the thermal pinched parameter analysis due to the uncertainty of  $v_e$ -Ar cross section
- Data analysis (python)

#### Jiangmen Underground Neutrino Observatory (JUNO)

China, 2015-2016

- Co-author of the JUNO Yellow Book (R&D tech notes)
- Sensitivity projection for the solar-captured DM in JUNO

# WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION

#### Mini-workshop on Novel Experimental and Astrophysical Probes for Dark Matter

*Taipei*, 2021

Main organizer of the workshop with Dr. Wu, Meng-Ru

# SUPERVISING EXPERIENCE

#### Co-supervisor of Academia Sinica Summer Student Program

*AS*, 2020-2022

- Co-supervising with Dr. Wu, Meng-Ru
- O Tsung-Han Tsai (now an undergraduate at NTHU), work published on Phys. Rev. D 108, 083013 (2023)
- Yong Sheng Yap (now a PhD student at Cambridge U), work on compact star equation of states in terms of neutrons and dark matter
- O Wen-Hua Wu (now a PhD student at Rice U), work published on Phys. Rev. Lett. 130, 111002 (2023)

#### Co-supervisor of SLAC Summer Student

UTSA/SLAC, 2020-2021

- O Co-supervising with Prof. Tanaka, Hirohisa (SLAC) and Dr. Tsai, Yun-Tse (SLAC)
- Adeela Malik (an undergraduate at Texas at San Antonio U), work on beyond Standard Model physics in supernovæ

#### Co-supervisor of NYCU Students

NYCU, 2020-2022

- O Co-supervising PhD/MS students from NYCU with Prof. Lin, Guey-Lin
- Aiming for beyond Standard Model physics in supernovæ/colliders and numerical support (Python/Mathematica)

# **GITHUB REPOSITORY**

#### snorer: Supernova-Neutrino-bOosted daRk mattER

- About: Evaluating the time-of-flight signatures of boosted dark matter due to supernova neutrinos from Milky Way, SN1987a and arbitrary distant galaxy.
- O Role: Main developer and maintainer
- o https://github.com/yenhsunlin/snorer

#### dukes: DiffUse-boosted darK mattEr by Supernova neutrinos

- O About: Evaluating the signatures of diffuse boosted dark matter by supernova neutrinos in the early Universe.
- O Role: Main developer and maintainer
- o https://github.com/yenhsunlin/dukes

#### dynesor: DYnamical NEsted Sampling integratOR

- O About: MCMC integrator for evaluating multidimensional integration based on dynamical nested sampling.
- O Role: Main developer and maintainer
- Non-disclose

#### **PROGRAMMING**

Python/Cython/C++/Mathematica/Matlab

# LIST OF PUBLICATION

# Yen-Hsun Lin Institute of Physics, Academi Sinica, Taipei

#### 1 Refereed Articles

Dagger ( $^{\dagger}$ ) and asterisk (\*) indicate that I am the *first author* and the *corresponding author*, respectively. Otherwise, the author list is arranged alphabetically.

- 1. **Y.-H. Lin**<sup>†,\*</sup> and M.-R. Wu, Supernova-neutrino-boosted dark matter from all galaxies, Phys. Rev. Lett. **133**, 111004 (2024)
- 2. **Y.-H. Lin**<sup>†,\*</sup>, T.-H. Tsai, G.-L. Lin, H. T.-K. Wong and M.-R. Wu, Signatures of afterglows from light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos in current and future large underground detectors, *Phys. Rev. D* **108**, 083013 (2023)
- 3. **Y.-H. Lin**<sup>†,\*</sup>, W.-H. Wu, M.-R. Wu and H. T.-K. Wong, Searching for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos, *Phys. Rev. Lett* **130**, 111002 (2023)
- 4. A. Bauswein, G. Guo, J.-H. Lien, Y.-H. Lin and M.-R. Wu, Compact dark objects in neutron star mergers, *Phys. Rev. D* **107**, 083002 (2023)
- 5. G.-L. Lin and **Y.-H. Lin**\*, Exploring dark sector parameters in light of neutron star temperatures, *Phys. Rev. D* **104**, 063021 (2021)
- 6. G.-L. Lin and **Y.-H. Lin**\*, Analysis on the black hole formations inside old neutron stars by isospin-violating dark matter with self-interaction, JCAP **08**, 022 (2020)
- 7. C.-S. Chen and **Y.-H. Lin**\*, *Reheating neutron stars with the annihilation of self-interacting dark matter, JHEP* **08**, 069 (2018)
- 8. C.-S. Chen and Y.-H. Lin\*, On the evolution process of two-component dark matter in the Sun, JHEP 04, 074 (2018)
- 9. C.-H. Chen and Y.-H. Lin, Study of  $B_c^{\pm} \rightarrow (D^0 K^{\pm}, D^0 \pi^{\pm})$  decays, arXiv: 1710.05531
- 10. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin, **Y.-H. Lin** and F. Xu, *The 17 MeV anomaly in beryllium decays and U*(1) *portal to dark matter, Int. J. Mod. Phys. A* **32**, 1750178 (2017)
- 11. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its impact on the indirect dark matter search, Phys. Dark Univ. 14, 35 (2016)
- 12. F. An et al. [JUNO Collaboration], Neutrino Physics with JUNO, J. Phys. G 43, 1 (2016)
- 13. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, Complementary test of the dark matter self-interaction by direct and indirect detections, JCAP 01, 013 (2016)
- 14. Z. Djurcic et al. [JUNO Collaboration], JUNO conceptual design report, arXiv:1508.07166

- 15. G.-L. Lin, **Y.-H. Lin** and F.-F. Lee, *Probing the coupling of heavy dark matter to nucleons by detecting neutrino signature from the Earth core*, *Phys. Rev. D* **91**, 033002 (2015)
- 16. C.-S. Chen, F.-F. Lee, G.-L. Lin and **Y.-H. Lin**, *Probing dark matter self-interaction in the Sun with IceCube-PINGU*, *JCAP* **10**, 049 (2014)

# 2 Conference Proceedings

- 1. International Conference on Topics in Astroparticle and Underground Physics, Vienna, Austria 2023 **Title:** *Searching light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos in Super-K, Hyper-K and DUNE*
- 2. International Conference on High Energy Physics, Bologna, Italy 2022 **Title:** Exploring dark sector parameters in light of neutron star temperatures
- International Conference on High Energy Physics, Prague, Czech 2020 (Webinar)
   Title: Analysis on the black hole formations inside old neutron stars by isospin-violating dark matter with self-interaction
- 4. PyCon TW, Taipei, Taiwan 2019 (Computer vision related) **Title:** The art of inference: Practicing Bayesian reasoning in computer vision problems
- 5. European Physical Society Conference on High Energy Physics, Ghent, Belgium 2019 **Title:** *Probing self-interacting dark matter through neutron stars*
- 6. International Conference on Neutrino Physics and Astrophysics, Heidelberg, Germany, 2018

  Title: On the evolution process of two-component dark matter in the Sun
- 7. International Symposium on Nuclei in the Cosmos, Niigata, Japan 2016 **Title:** Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its implication
- 8. European Physical Society Conference on High Energy Physics, Vienna, Austria 2015 **Title:** Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its implication
- 9. International Conference on High Energy Physics, València, Spain 2014 **Title:** The dark matter self-interaction and its impact on the critical mass for dark matter evaporations inside the Sun
- International Symposium on Particles, Strings and Cosmology, Taipei, Taiwan 2013
   Title: Probing the coupling of heavy dark matter to nucleons by detecting neutrino signature from the Earth core
- 11. International Symposium on Cosmology and Particle Astrophysics, Honolulu, Hawaii 2013 **Title:** Probing the coupling of heavy dark matter to nucleons by detecting neutrino signature from the Earth core

# 3 Domestic Seminars and Colloquia

TPS = Taiwan Physical Society.

- 1. Colloquium, Tunghai University, Taichung 2024
- 2. Seminar, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu 2024
- 3. Seminar, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu 2023
- 4. Seminar, Chung Yuan Christian University, Taoyuan 2023
- 5. Seminar, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei 2022
- 6. Seminar, National Taiwan University, Taipei 2022
- 7. Seminar, National Taiwan University, Taipei 2021
- 8. Seminar, Chung Yuan Christian University, Taoyuan 2020
- 9. Seminar, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei 2020
- 10. Webinar, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu 2020
- 11. Seminar, National Central University, Taoyuan 2020
- 12. Seminar, National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu 2020
- 13. Annual Meeting TPS, National Chiao Tung University Hsinchu, 2019
- 14. Colloquium, Tamkang University, New Taipei 2018
- 15. Seminar, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei 2018
- 16. Seminar, Academia Sinica, Taipei 2018
- 17. Seminar, National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu 2018
- 18. Seminar, Chung Yuan Christian University, Taoyuan 2017
- 19. Annual Meeting TPS, National Sun Yat-Sen University, Kaohsiung 2016
- 20. Annual Meeting TPS, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu 2015